Guide to the John L. De Forest / Sholem Asch Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John L. De Forest / Sholem Asch collection
1941-1995
1941-1943
GEN MSS 114
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
Collection consists of correspondence addressed to Asch, many letters carrying dictated drafts of his response on them. There are four typescripts of essays by Sholem Asch as well as five scripts for a Christmas pageant performed in Stamford, Conn., in 1943. Also present is De Forest's typescript memoir entitled, "My Hours with Sholem Asch."
Asch, Sholem, 1880-1957
Babb, James T. (James Tinkham), 1899-1968
De Forest, John L. (John Le Roy), 1916-
Gaebelein, Arno Clemens, 1861-1945
Garrett, Ellen Jeanette Lyttle, 1893-1970
Goodenough, Erwin Ramsdell, 1893-1965
Holmes, John Haynes, 1879-1964
Holzer, Hans, 1920-2009
Huebsch, B. W. (Benjamin W.), 1876-1964
Knollenberg, Bernhard, 1892-1973
Newman, Louis I. (Louis Israel), 1893-1972
Rosenwald, William, 1903-
Ziemer, Gregor Athalwin, 1899-
Zuckerman, Nathan, 1912-2000
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The John L. De Forest / Sholem Asch Collection was given by John L. De Forest in 1993.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
John L. De Forest acquired these papers while serving as Sholem Asch's secretary. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence addressed to Asch, many letters carrying dictated drafts of his response on them. There are four typescripts of essays by Sholem Asch as well as five scripts for a Christmas pageant performed in Stamford, Connecticut, in 1943. Also present is De Forest's typescript memoir (ca. 1991) entitled "My Hours with Sholem Asch."
Authors, Yiddish -- United States -- Archives; Asch, Sholem, 1880-1957 -- Archives; De Forest, John L. (John Le Roy), 1916-
- Box and Folder List
  - Correspondence
    - Drafts of letters from Asch
      - To A-Z, 1941-43 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Scope and Contents
        Asch, John
        Ferguson Library
        Freiheit
        [Shaffer], Ruth and Reg
        United Jewish Appeal
    - Letters to Asch:
      - "A" general, 1941-43 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Amalgamated Bank of New York
        American Jewish Congress
        Anspach, Marshall R.
        Astoria Press
      - "B-C" general, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Babb, James T. (James Tinkham)
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Yale University, Box 1, folder 15
        Community Church of New York
        Congregation Rodeph Sholom
        Includes letter from Asch to Congregation Rodeph Sholom
        Creative Age Press, Inc.
      - "D-G" general, 1942-43 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Dakin, Rodney G.
        Elliot, L. R.
        Gaebelein, Arno Clemens
        Garrett, Eileen Jeanette Lyttle
        See: Creative Age Press, Inc., Box 1, folder 3
        Goodenough, Erwin Ramsdell
      - "H" general, 1942-43 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Hartford Courant
        Heller, Judah G.
        Holmes, John Haynes
        See: Community Church of New York, Box 1, folder 3
        Holzer, Hans
        Huebsch, B. W. (Benjamin W.)
        See: Viking Press, Inc., Box 1, folder 13
      - "K-L" general, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Knollenberg, Bernhard
        Know Your Bible Company
        London Jewish Theatre
      - "M" general, 1943, n.y. (Box 1, Folder 7)
        McCullum, R. J.
        Monjo, J. M.
        Morris, Charles
      - "N" general, 1941-43 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        National Refugee Service, Inc.
        Newman, Louis I.
        See: Congregation Rodeph Sholom, Box 1, folder 3
        New York Committee of the National War Fund
      - "O-P" general, 1941-43 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Oxford University Press
        Princeton Theological Seminary
      - "R" general, 1941-43 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Raybond Theatres
        Rosenwald, William
        See: National Refugee Service, Inc., Box 1, folder 8
        Ruff, Mrs. G. Elson
      - "S-T" general, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Samuel, Gertrude
        Temple Beth Emeth of Flatbush
      - "U" general, 1942-43 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        United Jewish Laymen's Committee
        United States. Headquarters of the Commandant, Third Naval District
      - "V" general, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Viking Press, Inc.
        With draft of response by Sholem Asch
      - "W" general, 1941-42 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Who's Who in the East
        Writers Committee of United China Relief
        Wrubel, Jerry
        WSRR (Stamford, Conn.)
      - "Y-Z" general, 1942-43 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Yale University Library
        Ziemer, Gregor Athalwin
        See: Know Your Bible Company, Box 1, folder 6
        Zuckerman, Nathan
        See: American Jewish Congress, Box 1, folder 2
  - Writings by Sholem Asch
    - "The Birth of Hitler," typescript, corrected, p. [1]-3 only, 1943 Nov 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Christmas Story"
      - Program draft for presentation of "Christmas Story" at the First Congregational Church, Stamford, Connecticut, 1943 [Dec] (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Pageant director's copy, typescript, with stage directions, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
        Belonged to Arthur J. Sylvester
      - Organ script, typescript, with stage and organ directions (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Three scripts, typescript, with corrections and stage directions (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Katie Stieglitz," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Sholem Asch," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "Sholem Asch to Son," newspaper clipping, c. 1943 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Printed matter
    - Clipping from Yiddish newspaper "Forverts", 1995 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Musicians Committee of the National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, 1943 Nov 7 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Yale University News Bureau press release, 1944 Apr 16 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Stottler & Co., Inc., statement of account, 1941 Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Other Writings
    - De Forest, John L. "My Hours with Sholem Asch," typescript, corrected, c. 1991 (Box 1, Folder 29)